Guide to the Mel Rosenthal Photograph Collection 1983-2001 PR 90
New-York Historical Society
Mel Rosenthal Photograph Collection
1983-2001
New-York Historical Society
PR 90
1.84 Linear feet (2 boxes)
The collection consists of photographs of members of various refugee communities in New York state, including immigrants from Vietnam, the Ukraine, Haiti, Cambodia, and elsewhere.
Provenance
Purchase, 2001, and Gift, 2004.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Scope and Content Note
The Mel Rosenthal Photograph Collection spans the period from 1983 to 2001 and primarily contains photographs from his series documenting new immigrants to New York City and State. Individual prints are signed and captioned on verso by the photographer.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into two series: Refuge: The Newest New Yorkers; and General Photographs.
Gelatin silver prints.; New York (State) -- Photographs; Vietnamese Americans -- New York (State) -- Photographs.; Photographic prints.; Ukrainian Americans -- New York (State) -- Photographs.; Refugees -- New York (State) -- Photographs.; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Photographs.; Haitian Americans -- New York (State) -- Photographs.; Cambodian Americans -- New York (State) -- Photographs.
- Series I: Refuge: The Newest New Yorkers
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I includes a selection of images from Rosenthal's larger photo essay of this title. The collection consists of photographs of members of various refugee communities in New York state, including immigrants from Vietnam, the Ukraine, Haiti, Cambodia, and elsewhere. The photographs were taken between 1983 and 1999, and were reprinted in 2001 for the New-York Historical Society. The photo series was exhibited at the society in 1999, as well as many other venues.
  Photographs are filed chronologically.
  - Cambodian Children in the South Bronx, 1983 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Former Fisherman from Vietnam (Hempstead, Long Island), 1984 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cambodian Buddhist Monastery in the Bronx, 1985 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Amerasians getting married at the bride's home. Their fathers were American Service Men. Syracuse, 1992 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A Bosnian woman in a textile factory which employed hundreds of refugees. It was bought by a British company, closed and the machines moved "off shore." Central New York, 1992 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hmong women (Liverpool, NY), 1992 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Kurdish families, Johnson City, NY, 1992 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Russian Jewish immigrants playing chess in Brighton Beach, Brooklyn, NY, 1992 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sweet sixteen party of Vietnamese teenagers in Syracuse, NY. The words on the [karaoke] screen are "Forget the past. It will only hurt you.", 1992 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ukrainian wood carver, working at a furniture factory (Manlius, NY), 1992 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Vietnamese children watching "Aladdin" in Endicott, NY, 1993 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Adopted child from Russia at a naturalization ceremony at the New York Association for New Americans, Manhattan, 1994 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Amerasian gang leader inside cafe (Syracuse), 1994 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Haitian migrant woman (Putnam County, NY), 1994 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cambodian businessmen and a Buddhist monk at Tet Celebration in Brooklyn, 1995 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cuban families are among the most recent to arrive in Syracuse, 1995 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dancers from the Ukraine and Uzbekistan, Brighton Beach Ballet Theatre (Brighton Beach, NY), 1995 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Haitian police officer at the Caribbean Day Parade, Eastern Parkway, Brooklyn, NY, 1996 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Palestinian teenager roller blading in front of her father's electronic store in Bay Ridge, Brooklyn, NY, 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ukrainian children's dance group at Ukrainian Day celebration in East Village, New York City, 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II: General Photographs
  Series II includes other photographs taken by Rosenthal. This photograph, taken shortly after the terrorist attacks in September 2001, shows a Muslim woman with a photograph of her missing son.
  - Debbie Almontaser with photo of son Yousif, Brooklyn Heights, 2001, Sep. 16 (Offsite-box 1, Box 2, Folder 6)